[Music]
all right shall welcome to the scott
horton show i'm the director of the
libertarian institute editorial director
of antiwar.com
author of the book fool's aaron time to
end the war in afghanistan and the brand
new enough already time to end the war
on terrorism and i've recorded more than
5 500 interviews since 2003 almost all
on foreign policy and all available for
you at scotthorton.org you can sign up
the podcast feed there and the full
interview archive is also available at
[Music]
scott horton youtube.com
all right you guys i got john kiriakou
on the line and uh as you know he's a
former cia officer but he went to prison
for confirming the names of some cia
torturers to the uh um journalist
parenthesis question mark
uh matthew cole
and
so now he's a committed
one of us fighting against the national
security state writing the truth in this
case for responsible statecraft
and uh it's called supreme court to hear
whether abu's a beta's torture is secret
and check out this uh
i know it's not called really this the
sub headline there's a better name for
this the slug
i witnessed it all
20 years in gitmo without charge his
story remains our country's greatest
shame and boy john when you say i
witnessed it all you really mean welcome
back to the thing how are you doing
thanks for having me good to be with you
man so um you led the raid to capture
abu zabeda in pakistan go ahead and
first of all just tell us all about that
so especially for people who aren't that
familiar with you so they get a little
bit of a taste of who they're listening
to here
sure we we believed at the time that abu
zubaydah was the number three in al
qaeda that turned out to not be true but
he was a bad man he was he was a
logistician for al qaeda if you
wanted to um go home you were tired of
the fight abuza beta would get you a
fake passport and a ticket home he
created and ran al qaeda's two training
camps in southern afghanistan he created
and ran the house of martyrs safe house
in peshawar pakistan
so bad guy
but we thought he was the number three
incorrectly
at the time i was the head of cia
counterterrorism operations in pakistan
and we got word one day that he was in
pakistan we had to catch him it took us
about six weeks to track him down but we
finally did and we caught him he was
severely wounded during the capture a
pakistani policeman shot him with an
ak-47 three times no less
and uh i sat with him for the first 56
hours of his captivity then a cia plane
flew in picked him up and took him to
the first of what was a series of secret
prisons and then he's been in guantanamo
since 2006 but one of the main points
that i make in this piece
is that the man has never been charged
with a crime
that's after undergoing merciless uh
torture at the hands of the cia
83 times he was waterboarded his heart
stopped he drowned he had to be revived
so that he could be tortured some more
um he underwent sleep deprivation he was
put in a coffin for 11 years
slow down just a second there and just i
just want to remind you we got a little
bit of time here
so i don't want you to feel you're going
so fast it sounds like you feel like
you're gonna have to summarize too
quickly but
you have time to go ahead and elaborate
especially about this part like for
example
what how much of this you know
firsthand from being in the cia at the
time compared to what you learned in the
senate torture report all these things
we want to know
right
almost all of it i learned at the cia
when i got back from pakistan in the
middle of 2002 i got promoted and
on the strength of yabuza beta capture
and they made me the executive assistant
to the cia's deputy director for
operations so in that job i had access
to literally everything that the cia was
doing around the world
and um
you know absolutely was talking to the
fbi he was he was giving us information
that was new and fresh and it was
information on al qaeda that we had
never had before but the cia was angry
and jealous that the fbi was taking the
lead
uh george tenet asked president bush to
expel the fbi
and
and let the cia take over for reasons
that we don't understand bush agreed to
that and on august 1st 2002 the cia
began torturing him
so
you know they were supposed to start
with just
a shove right or you grab him by the
lapels and give him a shake that was the
plan the program but that's not where
they began they began with the most
serious torture technique and that was
waterboarding
and then it just got worse for him from
there
yeah and so now
it's funny because if you watch you know
some idiot reenacting this on youtube
uh waterboarding doesn't seem so bad i
saw one guy recently did a thing where
they had the cloth over his face folded
so many times i don't even think his
lips got wet you know right uh
what is it waterboarding is you're
drowning a guy almost to death over and
over again but in this case they
actually did kill him and had to shock
him back to life is that what you just
said exactly right his heart actually
stopped and he had to be revived that's
how bad it was
yeah and then talk about the coffin too
because you know they have said in the
past bugs
but you're a bit more specific here yeah
in the course of his interrogation
uh abazo beta
said that he had this what amounted to
an irrational fear of bugs he was just
freaked out by bugs
i don't know why he said it but he did
and so
the cia put him in this in this
coffin-like box there were several
different boxes
there was a dog cage they would just
open the door of the dog cage and and he
would whimper and just climb into it it
was you know that learned helplessness
but then they there was this coffin they
slept a diaper on him and they put him
in the coffin
and then they dumped a box of
cockroaches in on top of him and then
closed it and they would open it
each day only long enough
to change his diaper and to throw some
food in there with him and and with the
cockroaches but they did it just to make
him insane they knew that it would drive
him insane
yeah but wait a minute i'm sorry
it sounds like you're talking about some
anecdote from the 1940s in nazi germany
i thought we were talking about
something that the americans hadn't done
the cia to abu zubaydah
did i'm sorry i must have spaced out for
a second and lost track yeah seriously
seriously and you know what
in 1946
scott we executed japanese soldiers who
had waterboarded american pows that was
a death penalty offense
and i know i've said this before so
forgive me if i'm repeating myself but
in january of 1968 the washington post
ran a front page photograph of an
american soldier waterboarding a
vietnamese prisoner
the day that that picture ran
robert mcnamara the secretary of defense
ordered an investigation the soldier was
arrested he was charged with torture and
he was sentenced to 20 years in prison
well
the law never changed
so why was this a death penalty offense
in 1946 and worthy of 20 years in prison
in 1968 but then in 2002 no problem we
can do it we'll do a double zubato we'll
do it to a couple of other guys hey ed
niece ed meese uh the attorney general
under ronald reagan prosecuted the texas
sheriff for it in 1983.
see it's against the law it's against
the law and i say this all the time but
we are supposed to be a nation of laws a
nation ruled or or governed by the rule
of law
and we can't just decide that we're
going to ignore the laws that we don't
like
or the laws that don't fit into our
personal ideologically the anti-torture
laws
especially
uh yeah
i don't know little war crime statute
how does that measure up against the
do whatever you want as long as you cash
a federal government paycheck statute
um
now so
now when you say you know this from
being there and all of this just when
you're there in thailand you're telling
me you didn't torture the guy but you
were there or you were in the office
next door
listening through the wall or
what i'm i'm proud to say that i um i
refused
uh all trips to the secret sites to all
of them
i wanted no part of this at all and it's
funny you know a friend of mine told me
years later
i said you know everything got so hard
when i blew the whistle on the torture
program and he said no buddy he said
your problems began in 2002. when you
refused to be trained in the torture
techniques and they started referring to
you as the human rights guy he said in
the post-911 era at the cia that was not
a compliment you binko
it's true though that's what they
thought
i was not willing to
to you know go along
i was trouble
all right but then so in other words
you're sitting in the cafeteria and your
friends are going yeah here's what we
did to him or what yes
no i like i say in that position i had
access to to everything happening around
the world and this was a special
compartment
it was a very highly restrictive
compartment so
you know nobody nobody could talk about
it because most people didn't know about
it when when the torture program was
first created it was fewer than two
dozen people
in the world
knew that it was happening
that's how highly classified it was
and so you know it was
it was happening and they were reporting
back to headquarters here's what we did
this is what happened this is what how
we how he reacted but they were lying to
us
and they were telling us that he was
providing this actionable intelligence
in fact what they had done
is they knew
that the cia and the fbi reporting
channels were incompatible so they took
all of the fbi's reports about what he
had said during their their
interrogations they rewrote it in cia
channels and said well we waterboarded
him one time and here's what he said
look what he gave us he gave us
everything it's the whole kitchen sink
here
that is just incredible isn't it for and
and the thing is you got to rewind in
your brain the fox news narrative the
george w bush administration narrative
at the time
of oh man how crucial this was that and
it was zubaida above all who bush
invoked over and over again and this is
the number three guy in al qaeda he knew
all this stuff and we tortured him we
don't torture but we beat it out of them
all right
or whatever you call it and
um
so uh that was why it was so crucial and
then of course it's ron suskind tells
the story that he obviously got from
george tenet the chief of cia
that he told george bush in a briefing
hey it turns out this ubeda guy isn't
who we thought he was in fact right
remind me to ask you in a minute if i
bite and brain and forget it about the
cousin situation and all this stuff but
he he says to w bush this isn't uh you
know what we had told you before about
you know sorry boss
and bush said to tenet well you're not
gonna make me lose face on this are you
i said he was important in fact he had
said he was important over and over
again he was the number one main public
justification for the torture program if
they hadn't tortured zubaida they
wouldn't have been able to stop all
those plots they stopped and of course
in fact i need you to talk about this
part too um because there's very little
about this you know we can it's pretty
easy to find about sheikh al-libi but
they tortured lies about saddam hussein
out of abu zabada too didn't they oh
yeah sure they did you know let me tell
you real quickly about the conversation
between between bush and tenet
that account is true
and
condoleezza rice was was in the meeting
of course and when tenet objected
and said that you know he
we owed it to the public to tell the
truth about abu zubaydah that he wasn't
the guy we thought he was
um condi rice chimed in george
meaning george tenet she said george
you're just gonna have to take one for
the team
and i don't think i have
ever seen george tenet as angry as he
was that day that condi rice had spoken
down to him and told him he's gonna have
to take one for the team
he was livid
yeah well then and let me tell you a
little bit about the cousin that you
mentioned a second ago um well wait uh
hang on just on that for a second you
know the cia has a reputation because of
the neoconservatives and the pentagon
lying us into war digging through the
cia analyst trash and you know
repurposing it all and funneling all the
lies from the israelis and the uh the
iraqi national congress and all of this
stuff that yeah the poor old cia got
caught up in this or whatever but the
cia tortured lies about saddam hussein
out of at least two guys zubaida and
libby and and and these were used to lie
us into war and and i'm not certain
about zubaida maybe you can tell me but
al libby's lies were featured in
almost certain bush's state of the union
in them absolutely they were certain
that they were featured in colin
powell's u.n address in january of 2003.
that's right a libby
said under torture
exactly what the cia wanted him to say
and that was that there was a connection
between
al-qaeda and saddam hussein of course
there was no connection al-qaeda hated
saddam hussein as much as they hated the
united states
but
he gave us uh false information
that there had been a meeting
in uh in prague
between the iraqi station chief there
and muhammad atta the the head hijacker
we were supposed to believe that there
was this this connection whether it was
financial or logistical or whatever uh
between iraq and al qaeda it just simply
wasn't true
and so we went to
abu zubaydah to try to get the same
information and of course under under
torture under duress he confirmed the
information
and everybody knows that when you're
torturing somebody they will
admit to anything you want them to admit
to you
just so
that you can get them to stop
you don't just stop the the torture they
just can't take it anymore
hey y'all check out my new book enough
already time to end the war on terrorism
at
enoughalreadybook.net
early reviews are that people either
think it's hilarious or they get so
angry that they put it down but it's the
iranian revolution the 80s afghan war
the iran-iraq war iraq war one iraq war
one and a half and then afghanistan iraq
war ii somalia pakistan libya syria iraq
war iii yemen and all the special
operations wars throughout africa in the
aftermath of the war in libya
it's all there for you might change a
friend's mind enough already time to end
the war on terrorism at
enoughalreadybook.net
hey guys scott horton here for expand
expanddesigns.com
harley abbott and his crew do an
outstanding job designing building and
maintaining my sites and they'll do
great work for you you need a new
website go to expanddesigns.com scott
and say 500 bucks
hey guys check out listen and think
audiobooks they're listenanthink.com and
of course on audible.com and they
feature my book fools aaron time to end
the war in afghanistan as well as brand
new out inside syria by our friend reese
ehrlich and a lot of other great books
mostly by libertarians there reese might
be one exception but essentially they're
all libertarian audio books and here's
how you can get a lifetime subscription
to listen and think audiobooks just
donate 100 to the scott horton show at
scotthorton.org
donate
of course right like what would you do
seriously some of the things in here you
talk about and
you know there's a excellent book by
alfred mccoy where he talks about how
you know they claim here well they
copied this from the seer methods that
were copied from the communists to
protect our guys from the communists
when mccoy says no the truth is the
communists and the americans copied
these torture techniques from the nazis
and that's where all of this stuff comes
from and a lot of it is this kind of
no-touch torture oh gee all we did was
force him into the most uncomfortable
stress position and leave him tied up
like that for hours all we did was
freeze him almost to death over and over
again all he did was keep him up for
weeks and weeks and weeks but it's not
like we pounded nails
under his uh or you know spikes under
his fingernails or screws in the knees
so
you know therefore it's you know all we
did was give him a mega dose of lsd and
play new metallica and
strobe light and him drive him out of
his goddamn mind but it's not like we
beat him up or anything but i mean this
stuff gets really extensive right
especially the freezing i mean i'm cold
as hell if it's in the low 40s
you know i don't know
seriously and and what we did that's a
technique they called the cold cell
which i actually think is worse than
than waterboarding we we killed several
prisoners with the cold cell but what
they do is they they chain a a prisoner
to an eye bolt in the ceiling
so that he can't get comfortable in any
way he can't sit or lay down
and um and they strip him naked
they uh chill the cell to 50 degrees
fahrenheit and then every hour a cia
officer goes into the cell and throws a
bucket of ice water on him
and you know you can't withstand that
kind of treatment people died they died
of hypothermia
yeah that's crazy and i mean there's one
that they admit to this guy gol ramen
that they killed they froze to death in
the salt pit but you're telling me you
know for a fact that there's more than
him
oh yeah there's more than gold ramen
yeah
so now
i mean to be clear here man i mean the
the official record is
that two men
uh ramen and um
god damn it i knew his name one moment
ago um
uh jamadi uh right in abu ghraib was
hung from the ceiling with his arms
behind his back till it suffocated him
to death right did i get his name right
yes and and so
these are the two that officially
the cia were they were investigated by
durham the guy who's doing the sort of
quarter-ass job of prosecuting the
russiagate conspiracy right now is the
same guy who let the cia get away with
that and actually you told me before
john that
there were more people who sort of
disappeared people who died in custody
but nobody ever you know you guys keep
your secrets so you don't even tell each
other exactly
how people die or whatever but they just
go away and we know from um an eight you
know uh independent ap reporting and
also the claims of colin powell's former
chief of staff lawrence wilkerson that
there were 108 who died in military
custody and you know maybe some of those
were heart attacks but many of those
were tortured to death you know what i
mean those are you know whatever
illnesses
so many of them but how many how many
more people
died in cia custody that you know
about
like capital n know about not read in
the torture report but that you know
were because again that's those are the
only two in the torture report so who
else to be honest to god's truth i
probably shouldn't answer that
um but you gotta tell me that you know
it's
can you tell me you know it's more than
five or ten
for fifty
you know i
i don't want you to go back to prison
john but god dang man that's kind of
important
i would i would point people to to um
joe hickman's book about his experience
at guantanamo oh yeah see i left that
out
those three aren't admitted to but we do
know about those and it's the other
scott horton by the way when people look
up this story that's not me that's the
uh international human rights lawyer uh
the other scott horton uh law professor
at columbia university and um some sort
of editor i forgot the exact title
editor at harper's magazine who wrote
the incredible series of stories for
harper's about what joe hickman
witnessed and just very quickly in 2006
the cia murdered three guys at their
secret black site at guantanamo bay not
the military prison but the other one
over the hill uh it's called penny lane
or camp no
and so there's that so there's five but
you don't want to tell me about it
anymore because because if you read that
in harper's so did i and i interviewed
other scott about it at the time and it
was important but and and hickman's a
hero for telling that story but
hero i agree i agree but you know
something else
come on
more secrets well or at least tell if
you can really say that you know for a
fact that there were other people
tortured to death by the cia in the
black sites beyond the five that we've
now
you know discussed back and forth here
today then can you please tell us that
or not well i'll tell you
one of the things that the cia does is
it turns people over to
other countries
and then they're never heard from again
right but if i put it that way yeah
hey well that's easy enough i mean and
we already know that from robert bear
too so if you want to be interrogated
you send them to jordan if you want them
tortured you send them to syria
bashar al-assad and if you want him to
disappear forever you send him to egypt
exactly right yeah and i think he was
even talking about the clinton years i
don't even i don't even think he was
talking about during w bush yeah because
he he left during the clinton years yeah
i mean that was in the new statesman so
um
and i should say though that guy makes a
lot of claims that are completely
ridiculous lies
and including on russia gate and
including accusing the ayatollah of
doing 911 and whatever so but on that he
was
i'll buy it
sounds right to me
uh otherwise confirmed by multiple
sources too all right now so wait a
minute now tell me about the cousin here
sorry yeah so one of the things that
that
made us get the abuse of beta situation
so bloody wrong
was that abu zubaydah has a cousin
also named abu zabeda
and um
and you know in the cia we didn't know
that there were two abu zubaidas with
the same name
and so when you put both files together
this looks like a terrorist
superman right like how can this guy
it's amazing right yep this guy is
everywhere he's in different countries
and
carrying out operations and planning new
operations it's incredible
well it turns out it's because they're
two different people yeah and once
word got out that
quote unquote abu zubaydah was of
interest to the cia that was in time
magazine in early 2002
the the cousin abu zubaida fled
uh he he was in the united states and he
fled to jordan
and then just kind of disappeared
and nobody's ever seen him or heard from
him again
now we looked for him for ages but
couldn't find him
uh and then never publicly admitted
you know what we made a mistake we put
these two files together it's two
different guys never admitted it
so joe and i wrote this book
called the convenient terrorist
and like i'm you know compelled to do i
sent it to the cia for clearance
and they cleared it with no changes
so take that for what it's worth huh
i don't i don't know exactly how to take
that at all
well i have a few different ideas of how
i could take it like one there was a
really cool clearance guy who liked you
and your story and your work that week
or
um
lady
or
whatever he got nowadays i don't want to
pre-judge you know um
uh or
um
you're giving us a limited hangout but
it sure doesn't sound like it
so uh yeah no i don't know man
um very interesting and i'm sorry that i
have not read that book yet i have it
here on the pile of course
one of these days i'm going to stop time
and spend a year catching up on all
these books i should have already
finished reading all right i'm the same
way um but um all right and listen i'm
sorry because now we're running out of
time and i just realized that we haven't
really talked about this court case
going on in the state secrets and we
also i forgot to um uh ask you project
to talk about how they
took his eye out
without his permission that was part of
the torture that we missed
it's this is this is a crime against
humanity um abu zubaydah when we caught
him one of the first things that i
noticed was he had a a brown eye and
then a very
pale glassy
light blue eye that was clearly blind
and um it turned out that he had been
wounded by a piece of shrapnel
uh in afghanistan when he was fighting
the soviets
so
the eye never bothered him right like he
never said anything about it he never
complained about it and then one day
during his captivity
uh
he was sedated
he was taken into an operating room and
and his eye was taken
and when he woke up
he had
one eye
so the cia gave him a glass eye which he
has steadfastly refused to wear
uh because he had never consented to
having the eye removed so now he wears a
patch over his eye but you know this is
a very clear
case of of a crime against humanity you
just can't operate on someone
against his will you can't
remove an eye
against the guy's will
and again you know as a policy we never
ever apologize for anything
right
oh man um and so okay now he's still in
guantanamo bay they're never going to
put him on trial because anything they
do have on him is essentially negated by
the brutality and the torture that they
put this guy through and so they can't
give him a trial they still in 20 years
haven't figured out how to slap together
this ad hoc thing uh to hold real
military tribunals for these people
either so they're apparently just going
to hold them indefinitely but now he's
trying to sue
the he can't sue the cia they've got
sovereign immunity
like a british king or something like
that but he's trying to sue their
contractors who tortured him and it says
here in your piece that a federal
appeals court
had ruled in his favor and said that he
could sue
and now the cia is appealing to the
supreme court trying to say that because
of national security and the state
secrets privilege
they need to be able to
not even have a trial at all not have
secret testimony that only the judge
with top secret clearance can see back
in his chambers but not even have the
trial at all because that would reveal
secrets and then
you're kind of summarizing here
the rebuttal to that from the point of
view of his lawyers part of which is
that we do have this torture report and
as you mentioned here
we have i didn't even know this that
that porter goss michael hayden george
tenet and john mclaughlin all put their
names on a book called the rebuttal to
the cia uh the senate's torture report
here so yeah
people read it yeah oh i'm sorry
i think about eight people read it
oh yeah no i i'm sure i i didn't even
know the thing existed for crying out
loud um
but so
it sounds like he's got a pretty good
case here what you're saying is that
this stuff is already declassified all
that he needs to be able to prove his
case in court is already declassified
he's not even is am i right he's not
even necessarily asking for more things
to be declassified in his case or what
exactly
that's exactly right what he wants is
the two contract psychologists uh
bruce mitchell or j
bruce and j and james anyway mitchell
and jessen right uh he's asking that
they be
deposed
right under oath to confirm what they've
already said in their memoirs what
george tenet and porter goss and mike
hayden at all have already said in their
rebuttal what the senate torture report
has already said using declassified
cables
he's just asking for them to confirm
that yes indeed they tortured him
yeah so and then and then that's it
right it's not like he's gonna open up a
new bank account with his uh
winnings of punitive damages here or
anything like that he's just trying to
get force them to what admit it and say
sorry or what
pay them a dollar
and yeah admit it he doesn't even want a
sorry he he wants to be charged with a
crime he wants he wants some kind of of
finality to this thing you know the
guy's been incarcerated now it's going
to be 20 years on march the 22nd 20
years and i don't mean 20 years at a at
club fed
i mean 20 years of torture and solitary
confinement and secret prisons
and it's time for us to fish or cut bait
either charge for the crime or let him
go
man we're
we're still having this conversation
about guantanamo bay in 2021
man it's just unbelievable you know the
bush people said they wanted to close it
on the way out and then they didn't but
some of them even said that they support
i think robert gates um
you know wally was under obama said he
supported closing it they just never did
it they tried to move some of them to
trial in new york and then they all back
down
and that was the original that was the
original plan you know when
when i was still in pakistan uh my my
pakistani counterpart came to me one day
it was brigadier general and he said
listen our jails are full because every
time we'd catch al-qaeda people we would
just stick them in the local jail
raul pindi lahore you know peshawar
wherever we happen to catch him we just
stick him in jail and and we filled the
jail
the jails
so he said you guys are going to have to
do something with these al-qaeda people
we can't hold any more of them
so i cabled headquarters and i said the
jails are full here what do you want us
to do with the prisoners
and they said put them on a c-12 and
send them to guantanamo
and i said
guantanamo cuba
and they said yeah we have an idea we're
going to hold them in guantanamo for
three or four weeks until we can figure
out what federal district to charge them
in
either boston new york or washington
uh-huh
and i said yeah that's a great idea
and here we are 20 years later
and they still haven't been charged with
any crimes
yep
man it's just
and you know but the biden people have
said that they want to close it you take
that seriously at all or we're just
going to have the same conversation
another 20 years from now
no i i think that biden wants to close
it and i think obama wanted to close it
but you know
the congress under the republican
congress under obama passed a law that
obama was pressured into signing saying
that
that the federal government can't
appropriate any money for the purpose of
shutting down guantanamo
so it's not going anywhere
yeah
man
all right well there you go and that's
the other interview today is gareth
porter on the self-licking ice cream
cone and exactly military projects that
can never end and must never end
so there it is
all right well thank you so much for
your time john great to talk to you
great to talk to you thanks for having
me not you guys that's john kiriyaku he
used to be a cia analyst then he was the
cia actual uh officer out there and then
uh he went to jail and now he's
an author and a journalist and he wrote
the convenient terrorist
with joseph hickman the same guy who was
the heroic whistleblower from the cia
murder of those three men in 2006 down
there at guantanamo as well so uh
go and read that stuff thanks oh this
one i'm sorry is uh
responsiblestatecraft.org
supreme court to hear whether abu's
debate is torture is secret
the scott horton show anti-war radio can
be heard on kpfk 90.7 fm in la
apsradio.com
antiwar.com
scotthorton.org
and libertarianinstitute.org